RG 003, New London County Court African Americans and People of Color Collection
Connecticut State Library
The court also heard nine lawsuits involving runaway slaves, five from before and four after the Revolution. The final runaway case was heard in February 1800, Jonathan Starr v. Rufus Smith and Jasper Latham. Primus Negro ran away from Jonathan Starr of New London on February 12, 1799. He secured passage on the sloop Speculator to the Port of New York thanks to the assistance of the two defendants. Primus was captured, for some reason entrusted to the two defendants, and again escaped. Starr sued for two months lost services and the expenses incurred to return him.46
In addition, a tiny number of additional cases involved attempts to enslave (7) and kidnapping (2) after Connecticut's 1784 gradual emancipation statute. Perhaps the most interesting was Caesar Peters v. John Mann and Nathaniel Mann, December 1789. As the original writ stated, some two years earlier, the plaintiff together with his wife, and their eight minor children were at home, "all at peace with the Good Citizens of this State and about his Lawful Business, Being Intituled to Liberty and the protection of the Laws of this State as a Citizen thereof," despite the fact they were "of the Complection of the Inhabitants & Natives of Africa, who have Been By Sundry of the more Barbarous European natives Considered as Slaves." The defendants broke into their house and kidnapped the family "for the Purpose of Transporting them to Some Foreign Country." They were placed in chains and taken to Preston to be put on board a ship sailing for slave country, but were rescued by a number "of the Good Citizens of this State." Peters sued for £2,000 damages. His lawsuit was unsuccessful and he appealed to the Superior Court.47
The suits for trespass cover a variety of subjects. The court classified the three cases of Adam Rogers v. Joseph Bolles, referred to earlier in which the defendant had forcibly evicted Rogers' wife and daughter from their house, as trespass. In another case, Hagar Wright v. Rebecca Chesebrough, the plaintiff accused the defendant of breaking into her house in Groton and forcibly carrying away a mulatto girl named Mary Right.48 In June 1743, Samuel Ely and others sued Richard Ely for trespass. Richard's servant Tonney Negro had entered the land of the plaintiffs, cut down, and carried away timber valued at £15. The court found the defendant guilty and he appealed.49 Lt. John Clark of Saybrook sued William Ely of Lyme for trespass, specifically for entering the plaintiff's house, imprisoning the family, and making off with his servant Zaccheus. Ely was also convicted and he likewise appealed.50 In John Willcocks 2nd v. Thomas Griffith, the defendant, Boston who was a Negro servant, an apprentice, and an Indian servant were accused of trespass for tearing down the plaintiff's fence and allowing his livestock to escape. The defendants were all convicted, fined, and ordered to pay court costs.51
Perhaps the most intriguing case in the entire collection is found under the subject of theft, "Cezar a Mollatto Man of Norwich, Vers. Jubee, Negro Man of Groton, a Slave for Life to Capt. Chris[tophe]r Avery." Cezar accused Jubee of "feloniously taking 1000 Spanish Mil[le]d Dollars, 500 Pistol[e]s, and 50 Double Double Loons Spanish money" worth £5,000 in Connecticut bills of credit. The plaintiff claimed that Jubee had stolen the Spanish coin from a large wooden box in his house. Under questioning from Assistant Hezekiah Huntington, Jubee gave evasive and unconvincing testimony, but the jury acquitted him.52 We know nothing further about the case and these two men. How was it possible for Cezar to acquire such a large sum of money, assuming that he was not engaged in some gigantic fraud? After all, £5,000 would make its legal owner one of the richest men in New London County. Had Cezar stolen then money, perhaps in the Caribbean? Was it prize money? Was the coin stolen by Jubee and "laundered' by confederates, because it was never found? Had Jubee been tempted by the thought that it was impossible for any white man to believe Cezar's tale of great riches, thus the theft could be undertaken with virtual impunity? We simply do not know.
The remaining six theft cases for the pre-Revolutionary War period take on a more normal pattern. In John Hurlbut v. James Right, the plaintiff affirmed that Right, "A Molato man... Servant to Andrew Davis of Groton," stole a white mare, saddle, and bridle worth £35.53 The court found Right guilty and sentenced him to pay treble damages of £165 together with court costs. Unable to pay, the court ordered that the defendant be whipped and assigned to the service of Hurlbut for fourteen years.54 People of color were involved in around 100 cases of theft in the post-Revolutionary War era.55 Files for April 1815 contain records of the non-prosecuted case of the State v. Sarah Pomp of North Stonington who was accused of stealing clothing and other household goods worth $60 from Newcomb Kinney. Two other people of color, Prudence Robinson of Bozrah and Silas Aaron of Groton were also arrested and Pomp was jailed after she failed to secure bond for her court appearance.56 In November 1830, George Derry, "a man of color," was convicted of "feloniously & burglariously breaking & entering" the stores of Robert Jackson, Nathaniel Saltonstall, Robert Coit, and Samuel Hurlburt in New London and sentenced to six years at Wethersfield State Prison.57 In a last example, Horace Thompson of Stonington, "a man of color," was tried and convicted of stealing a horse worth $70 and given a two-year sentence at State Prison.58
The collection includes seven cases of assault and battery from the earlier period and more than 140 for the later one. The African American servant is the victim of the attack in most instances in the colonial period. On June 13, 1772, John Leach of New London attacked a Negro boy named Cezar, the servant of Christopher Christophers. The boy was injured and Christophers had to pay medical expenses in addition to being deprived of the youth's labor. He sued for forty shillings damages. In a trial before a justice of the peace, the defendant was found guilty. Required to pay five shillings damages and court costs of £1-0-10, the defendant appealed to the county court where the case was continued.59 Rufus Minor and Samuel Minor, Jr. of Stonington filed a complaint on March 29, 1737 against three white men, a "negro man named Jack & two indian men" for assault. The local justice of the peace bound the miscreants over to the county court, but the case was ultimately withdrawn.60
Free people of color were also often victims of crime, as for example, Prince Williams of Groton who was violently attacked by Nathan Crary, Jr. with a club. Williams suffered a fractured scull and blows to the body that rendered him incapacitated. He sued for £200 pounds damages and settled out of court.61 In November 1836, State's Attorney Jirah Isham brought a complaint against Wheeler Morgan for assaulting, stabbing, and dangerously wounding Eber Quy of Norwich.62 To cite one example of an all too common crime, the State accused George Jackson of New London for assaulting his wife Elizabeth, "by striking her repeated blows, with his fists on the breast, and... threatening that he would finish her, and would kill her." The case was never brought to trial on the grounds of insufficient evidence.63 African Americans, however, were perpetrators as well as victims of crime, as in the case of State v. Benjamin Olney of New London who was accused of assaulting George W. DeWolfe in September 1852.64 Assaults and threats thereof comprised almost all crimes of violence involving people of color from the time of slavery until the mid-19th century.
The other two categories of criminal conduct represented by significant numbers can be characterized as sex crimes and those involving alcoholic drink. The King's Attorney and State Attorney prosecuted 23 men and women for crimes associated with prostitution, 22 for adultery, 12 fornication, and 3 lascivious carriage. The State instituted 23 prostitution related offenses between 1842 and 1850. For example, in August 1842 Prince Williams of Preston was charged with keeping and maintaining "a House... reputed to by a house of bawdry and Ill fame," although the State's Attorney declined to prosecute, while in June 1850 Sarah Richards of New London was convicted of prostitution, fine $10, and obliged to pay court costs of $18.30.65 In June 1851, the State prosecuted both Josephine Mead and Henry Benton of New London for adultery. Josephine, wife of Edward Mead, was charged with "carnal knowledge of the body of Henry Benton," but the case was nollied after she agreed to testify against Benton. Benton was found guilty and sentenced to two years at Wethersfield State Prison.66 The handful of fornication cases include that of a lawsuit by Thankful Warris of Lisbon suing a minor after she became pregnant with his bastard child and James Guy of Norwich who was accused of committing fornication with a minor and inducing her to become a prostitute.67
Blacks are mentioned in eighteen cases that concern the illegal sale of alcoholic beverages. Lemuel Henry of New London, "not being a taverner," was brought before the county court on four occasions in 1846 and 1847 for selling "spirituous liquors" by the glass from his shop.68 Six years later the State prosecuted Benjamin Bacon, also not a licensed taverner, for the illegal sale of liquor to David Frost, Joseph Cross, and David Frost, Jr.69
The African American Collection contains materials on a number of other subjects. A few examples provide additional information on the kinds of cases found.
In June 1807, Jeremiah Tracy of Lisbon sued Pero Moody for violating the statute regulating fisheries by drawing a seine across the Quinebaug River at a time not sanctioned by law.70 Several months later John Burwell and others, owners of the brigantine Dove, brought suit against Levi Meeds, "a transient black man," on charges of desertion in violation of a federal law to regulate seamen in merchant service.71 The State brought charges against Zebulon Parkis, Jr. in 1845 for disturbing a temperance meeting at the Methodist Episcopal Church in Norwich.72 Robbins Babcock was prosecuted in December 1848 for throwing stones at a train of the Norwich and Worcester Rail Road in Lisbon. He was acquitted.73
The county court dealt with five cases of cruelty, three of which involved James Rogers of New London. In two 1755 cases, both called Dom Rex v. James Rogers, the King's Attorney for New London County sued Rogers for cruelty to his slave Sharper. The defendant had "in a forceable manner drove a nail... Thro one of the Ears of him sd. Sharper and Nail'd the Same fast to the wall." The jury acquitted the defendant.74 In the last case, James Rogers v. Giles Goddard, the plaintiff sued for £400 old tenor damages. Rogers owned a 25-year old slave name Abner who was healthy and sound except for two sores, one on his left elbow and the second "near his Privete Parts." The sores were not serious enough to prevent Abner from doing farm work. Rogers asked Dr. Goddard to cure the sores and he agreed to do so. Abner was sent to the doctor's house and he did "in a Cruel and Unreasonable Maner... with a lance or some sharp instrument made an Invasion into the lower Part of the Right shoulder of the said Negro in a sound Part of his body where there was no sore before and then Cut out Part of one of the sinews of his said shoulder and thereby Grieviously maimed and wounded said Negro." Abner lost the use of his right arm and the wound had not healed. The defendant was found not guilty and the plaintiff appealed to the Superior Court.75
Three cases found under three different subjects between 1762 and 1764 concerned Titus Mando.761 In the first case, Titus v. Jabez Lothrop of Norwich, the plaintiff sued for £12 in a debt by book "for work and Labour Done." The defendant argued that Titus was a slave for life, but the court disagreed and ordered Lothrop to pay Titus £12 damages. The defendant appealed. The second case was Jabez Lothrop v. Amariah Bozworth. Suing for £50 damages, the plaintiff accused the defendant of enticing his slave for life to leave his service. The court deemed the declaration of the plaintiff insufficient and he again appealed. Documents in this lawsuit and in Jabez Lothrop v. Joseph Fowler of East Haddam, formerly of Lebanon, in a plea of covenant broken provided evidence that Titus, son of Phillis, was free born and, therefore, Fowler had no right to sell the boy.77
Some records contain a treasure trove of information about several people of color, for example, a riot in New London in 1831. The State's Attorney charged Peggy Sansom, Benjamin Burton, John Rhodes, Lucy Rhodes, and John Smith, "all persons of color," with being "rioters, routers and disturbers of the peace" by breaking into the house of Benjamin Beach on the night of July 5 and terrifying the residents. Five adults living in the house were called as witnesses - Benjamin Beach, Ann Beach, Frank Neads, Mariah Neads, and Nancy Freeman. Sansom, Burton, and Rhodes were bound over for trial. The three failed to appear for trial and defaulted on their bonds.78 Eleven years later Norwich grand juror Charles Clark accused William Johnson, Felix Ruggles, James Peckham, Luther Peckham, William H. Brown "and divers other persons... unknown of said Town" on December 31, 1841 of disturbing a meeting and destroying property of the "Colored Ecclesiastical society" of Norwich. Thirteen members of the congregation were summoned as witnesses and the defendants were bound over to the February session of the county court. The case was continued and, after tempers had cooled, the defendants were not prosecuted.79
Other court records contain more tangential references to people of color, as when they are called as witnesses or mentioned in some other context. One such example from Files can be characterized as playing the race card. The November 1763 court convicted Samuel Atwell, Jr. of arson for burning down the full barn of Jedidiah Chapel of New London. The court ordered Atwell to pay £125-9 damages and £7-14 court costs.80 The next February Atwell petitioned for a rehearing of his case. He argued that new evidence existed that pointed to a runaway Negro man called Will as the culprit. The court refused to grant Atwell a rehearing.81 In a case of the theft of a cow from December 1813, Pardon Brayton was one of several witnesses called, while another that same session, John Noyes on behalf of the inhabitants of Lyme sued Charles Smith, as executor to the will of Marshfield Parsons, for the costs of caring for Basil, a "negro servant & Slave for life.82 The March 1824 court heard the debt case of William Tucker & Denison B. Tucker v. Pachog Manufacturing Company of Griswold. The debts totaling $214.43 included orders from James Watson, Harry Bennett, Fall Pellum, Sim Simons, and Joseph Simons, all people of color.83 One last example of lawsuits that mention people of color comes from June 1835 in which Lydia Bulkeley of New Haven sued Oliver Raymond of Lyme on a debt by note for $250. Landed property of the defendant was attached to ensure that he would appear at trial, land that bordered on the property of several others, including the heirs of Prince Brown and Lucy Crosby.84
Additional data is found in the Papers by Subject series of New London County Court Records. As indicated above, eighty-five records of people of color have been found who are not represented in Files. The bulk of them come from three series - Costs (39), Revolutionary War Pensions (20), and Summons for Evidence (14). The remaining dozen are divided among Executions (5), Conservators and Guardians (2), Court Expenses (2), Miscellaneous (2), and Confiscated Estates and Loyalists (1). In another 160 cases, the new information supplements that already found in Files, primarily from three series - Costs, Executions, and Summons for Evidence. Just over 20% of all records contain information derived at least in part from Papers by Subject.
Costs comprise the largest number of Papers by Subject records and consist almost exclusively of bills submitted to pay the expenses of jail prisoners. For example, in December 1819 prison keeper John Lawrence submitted a bill for $5.50 to the county court, $4.50 of which was for the feeding and jail fee for Jack Bennet who was accused of theft. The following March a bill for $63.35 included $9.21 for expenses incurred by James Robbins.85 For the period from 1839 to 1850, the jailers provided lists of prisoners with the amount owed for the care of each. An early list for February 1840 lists ten people of color on three pages - Edmund Freeman, Harvey Hyde, James Kimo, Caroline Lazier, John Lazier, Louisa Lazier, Samuel Lewis, Phebe Orchard, Abraham Peters, and John Smith.86
Revolutionary War Pensions make up the next largest number of records. The United States Congress in 1818 passed legislation granting pensions to non-disabled veterans of the War of Independence. Subsequent legislation in 1820 limited pension rights only to those living in poverty.87 Papers by Subject holds 154 alphabetically arranged pension applications, twenty of which were for people of color and four for Indians. All dating initially from June 1820, the petition of Peter Peters of Stonington is representative of the group as a whole. The petition was written by Charles Lathrop, clerk of the county court, and signed by Peters with a mark. Peters stated that he enlisted in the Continental Army in November 177, served for three years in First Connecticut Regiment commanded by John Durkee, and re-enlisted to serve for the duration of the war. Now age 65, he was infirm and without a family. His property consisted solely of clothes worth a little over $10.88
Summons for Witnesses is the last series to contain significant new information. In June 1735, Adam Rogers, Jr. was summoned to appear as a witness in the case between Joseph Talman and Moses Rowley and twenty years later "Ann a molatto wench" was summoned to give evidence in the case between John Huglison and Pardon Tabor.89 Of the remaining items, just one stands out from the Conservators and Guardians series. On March 14, 1808, Thomas Halsey of Groton petitioned the county court. Saying that he had been born a slave and manumitted by Jeremiah Halsey, Esquire, in 1779, he had acquired an estate worth $2,500. Notwithstanding his prosperity and enjoying "the privileges of a Citizen in all Respects except the Right of Suffrage," the selectmen of Groton had appointed an overseer over him two weeks previously. He asked the court to "Liberate your Petitioner from the power and Controul of sd. Overseer" and restore him to his "Natural Rights and privileges of a Citizen." The court granted his petition."90
The bulk of the information found in Papers by Subject, however, supplements that contained in Trials primarily in the series for Costs, Executions, and Summons. The case of Cezar v. Jube, described earlier, holds additional documentation in both Costs and Summons for Evidence.91 After Stephen Nott recovered judgment against Zaccheus Still of Saybrook in June 1761 for £5-1-5 debt and £1-15 costs of suit, Papers by Subject provides information on the exact nature of the costs. They consist of cost of writ one shilling and a six pence, officers fees seven shillings and six pence, travel four shillings four pence, and court fees and attendance totaling £1-1-3.92
The county court issued writs of execution to losing parties in lawsuits to recover the debt incurred and costs of lawsuits. Boxes 12 and 13 contain almost ninety executions levied by or upon African Americans. In June 1818 after Pero Moody of Lisbon recovered judgment against Isaac S. Moody for $94.29 debt and costs of suit, a constable on July 20, 1818 went to the house of Isaac Moody and seized a feather bed, gun, and articles of clothing to be sold at auction.93 Sometimes the execution takes the form of sentencing documentation for criminal offenses, as in June 1836 when Oliver H. Perry Lewis was convicted of burglary and sentenced to two years in Connecticut State Prison and costs of prosecution $18.42.94
The African American and People of Color Collection, then, has considerable research value for those with biographical, genealogical, and historical perspectives and provides documentation that helps trace the history of slavery and freedom in New London County.
Endnotes
2Cross checking of Costs and Executions in Papers by Subject has led to most of the additions to the original numbers.
3Mulatto is used in 19 no surname cases. Most were probably of mixed Negro and Indian blood.
4Blacks were parties in numerous debt cases at the county court level, more than 500 for the period after the American Revolution, but, since it is likely that the sums involved were often modest, many more suits were heard by single justices of the peace at the town level.
5John Jackson, Hagar Wright, and Adam Rogers were all at one time servants of James Rogers of New London. arbara W. Brown and James M. Rose, joint authors, Black Roots in Southeastern Connecticut, 1650-1900 (Detroit: Gale Research Co., 1980), 201, 349, 452. The Jackson names found are Adam, John, Jane, and Peter, plus others listed as Abner, Joan, and Miriam and designated as Negro. An Isaac Rogers of New London is found in six lawsuits between 1799 and 1824 but no evidence exists that he was related to Adam Rogers.
6George Glasko is found 7 times and Jacob Glasko 3.
7Black Roots, 196-97; James M. Rose and Barbara W. Brown, Tapestry: A Living History of the Black Family in Southeastern Connecticut (New London: New London County Historical Society, 1979), 71-74.
8Rose and Brown, Tapestry, 71-72; Guocun Yang, "From Slavery to Emancipation: The African Americans of Connecticut, 1650s - 1820s (Ph.D., University of Connecticut, 1999), 243-44.
9Nov. 1732, Box 1, folder 37. All box and folder references are made to New London County African Americans Collection. Those interested in the place where the originals were located can find that information on the folders in the African Americans Collection.
10In the records, she is called Joan Negro. Children Abner and Peter are generally called Abner Negro and Peter Negro.
11June 1710, Box 1, folder 2. See also Allegra Hogan, "'Buzzelling' as Historical Method: In Praise of Genealogy," Connecticut History 40 (Fall 2001): 255-57.
12June 1711, Box 1, folder 3.
13Brown and Rose, Black Roots, 450-53.
14June 1710, Box 1, folder 3. The boy was probably Wait Wright who was about twelve and one half.
15Nov. 1716, Box 1, folder 7.
16Currency was denominated in pounds, shillings, and pence until the late 1790s. Each unit was separated by a dash, thus £2-17-5 equals 2 pounds, 17 shillings, and 5 pence. Twenty shillings make up a pound and twelve pence a shilling. Some debts are counted in fractions of pennies, called farthings. Four farthings make one penny. Connecticut depended almost exclusively on paper currency, called bills of credit. The colony's original currency, called old tenor, had seriously depreciated by the 1740s, so that it took five to ten pounds of old tenor to be equivalent to one pound of lawful money.
17Feb. 1751, Box 2, folder 15. This lawsuit is found among the No Docket cases for which there was no verdict. Wright may have withdrawn the action.
18See below for more information on Catherine Jones.